Welcome to Mariners Online. My name is Steve Bae and I'm one of the pastors. It is an absolute joy to be with you today. Do you own or do you know anyone who owns a rubber duck? Not a trick question. How about this follow-up question? Do you regularly talk to or do you know someone who regularly talks to their rubber duck? Probably not. And even if that was like, you know, your hobby, your favorite thing to do in the entire world, it's probably not something you want to announce on social media anytime. In fact, if you saw me walking down the street talking to a rubber duck followed by my four kids like little ducklings talking to their own rubber ducks, you should probably, I don't know, call the police.
But what if I told you that talking to a rubber duck is a proven method for problem-solving? Rubber duck debugging or rubber ducking is a concept that first emerged in the software engineering world. One of the authors from the book called The Pragmatic Programmer tells a story about a man named Greg who was an amazing, amazing software developer.
And he noticed that anytime Greg ran into a problem, a coding problem, he would sure enough pull out his rubber duck and he would talk out the issue with the rubber duck. And here's what the author says. The act of explaining step by step what the code is supposed to do often causes the problem to leap off the screen and announce itself. Verbally processing to a rubber duck somehow solved problems. Odd, bizarre, strange, and yet an effective method for problem solving.
I share this because today we're going to continue our series in the book of Numbers. And we find God today solving a problem in the most bizarre, strange, and odd way. But when we get underneath the story, it's actually about God's bizarre and strange love for you. But I don't want to get ahead of myself. Let's first find out what the problem God's people experienced. Then they set out from Mount Hor by the way of the Red Sea to bypass the land of Edom. But the people became impatient because of the journey. The people spoke against God and Moses.
Why? Why have you led us up from Egypt to die in the wilderness? There's no bread or water and we detest this wretched food. Then the Lord sent poisonous snakes among the people and they bit them so that many Israelites died. Okay, so the people grumble against God and so God sends poisonous snakes to bite them and many people are dying in the wilderness. Just a totally normal passage in the scriptures. Welcome to church. Okay, what's going on here? Is God overreacting? Because, you know, my kids complain and I've never locked them up in a room with poisonous snakes. Yet.
Like, what's going on here? Well, according to the text... We can know that the people are not simply raising up a concern in innocence. No, they're actually attacking the very character of God. They're not innocently raising a concern. They're assuming the absolute worst about God. We know this because of their accusation. They say, why have you led us up from Egypt to die in the wilderness? There's no bread or water and we detest this wretched food. Do you hear their layers of accusation?
First, they say that God essentially has murderous intentions. They're like, you brought us out here so you can kill us yourself. Then secondly, they say he's negligent, that he's an awful provider. Did you notice their contradiction? They make sense. They're like, "You don't give us food. You don't give us food. And we hate the food that you give to us." It's nonsensical. It's illogical. They don't make sense. But that wasn't their goal. Their goal was not to make sense. Their goal was to accuse God of not making sense.
This is character assassination at its finest. This is a full assault on the character of God. This isn't backstabbing, by the way. This is frontstabbing. How? How could the people respond this way, especially after God, I don't know, rescued them from their oppression and provided them for the last 40 years, housing them and taking care of them? Their goal was to accuse God of not making sense. This is character assassination at its finest. This is a full assault on the character of God. This isn't backstabbing, by the way. This is frontstabbing.
How? How could the people respond this way? Especially after God, I don't know, rescued them from their oppression and provided them for the last 40 years, housing them and taking care of them. The BBC, they reported a lifeguard who was fired for leaving his station to try to go and rescue a drowning person. As you can imagine, this led to public outcry. How can you fire someone who's trying to rescue a lifeguard, who's trying to rescue a drowning person?
But what's happening in our story here in Numbers would be akin to as if the man who was rescued himself, as if he were the one who fired the lifeguard himself. As if he was rescued, then he was housed by the lifeguard for 40 years and then concluded, hey, Mr. Lifeguard, you're awful. Life was way better when I was drowning in the ocean. You're fired. That's a little bit of what's happening in the story. It is a slap in the face of God.
So how could human beings respond this way to their creator? Now, here's what some people might say. Some people might say it's because of circumstance. It's circumstantial. I mean, we know this. I mean, even the best of people, when they're put in bad circumstances, they can turn into bad people. Now, to be fair, the people of God in the story, their circumstances were bad. That is true. We know this because of the hint in our passage. We're told. Then they set out from Mount Hor by way of the Red Sea to bypass the land of Edom.
Now, this was an emotionally charged and loaded statement. So just to give you a visual, here's where God's people are right now. They're at Mount Hor, where that star is, and they're trying to reach Canaan. It's been a 40-year journey, and guess what? They see the light at the end of the tunnel. It's right there. And better yet, there's a shortcut. There's a shortcut through the land of Edom. This shortcut was called the King's Highway. But the kingdom of Edom would block this pathway, which you could read about in the chapter previously.
They blocked this pathway. So here's what this meant. It meant that the people had to backtrack. They had to go backwards. They had to go back down south and go all the way around Edom. Could we just confess, you and I are not even the best people and we need to make a U-turn on the freeway. Could we confess that? Like in the mornings after I get my kids ready for school and after a chaotic, crazy morning, when I'm just about to drop them off at school on time and one of them says, whoops, I forgot my lunch. How do you think I react?
How do you think I react as a godly, loving father, as a pastor who serves his people? Here's what I say. Then you must starve. You must pay for your crimes against humanity. They backtracked. And so some people will say circumstances. But God, in his infinite wisdom, he would offer a different diagnosis. God would not say circumstances. God would actually say it's a condition. It's a spiritual condition of the heart. See, that's why God sent these snakes in the wilderness.
It wasn't some petty form of retaliation. No, see, God was trying to pull the curtain back to show them what was really going on. He was trying to take them under the hood to show deeper spiritual significance, namely, that long before these snakes ever showed up in the wilderness, they had already been bitten. They've already been poisoned. There was spiritual venom that was already coursing through their hearts and their souls. How do we know this? For our people in the story, this concept of a snake, it would not have been new for them.
In fact, the idea of a snake would have been very familiar for them, going back not just to their own history, but further back to the very history of humankind in Genesis. Because there was a snake or a serpent in the garden. God had created a beautiful and perfect world. Then he created Adam and Eve, and he placed them in the garden with unlimited provision and his very own presence. But when the serpent showed up, he began assassinating God's character.
The serpent said, hey, are you guys happy? You sure? You sure you're doing good? Did God actually say? And when Adam and Eve, when they believed the serpent's lies, and when they sinned, when they sinned by biting into that fruit, it was sin itself that actually bit. The fangs of sin dug into their hearts and their souls, poisoning their hearts and poisoning all of us spiritually and killing all of us spiritually. We've been spiritually poisoned.
That's why all of us, all of humanity, we have this strange insatiable thirst. Have you noticed that? Nothing is enough for us. Nothing is ever enough for us. In fact, we humanity, we think even God is not enough for us. We can never be happy, never satisfied, never content. This is the condition of every single generation. This is why every new generation arises with brand new ways to be happy. And in fact, with advanced technologies, we try to accelerate our joy, and we're never happy.
It's never enough. We've been spiritually poisoned. It's not circumstance. If anything, our circumstances simply reveal and expose our underlying condition of what's already happened. And that's why God sent these snakes, these serpents in the wilderness. Some Bible scholars have said that one of the effects of the bites of a certain kind of snake in this region, it would have been an intense, insatiable thirst. See, the bite in the wilderness was a mirror of the bite in the garden.
The insatiable thirst in the wilderness mirrored the insatiable spiritual thirst that we now experience ourselves. The death in the wilderness mirrored the death that now fell on humanity from the fall in the garden. We have a problem. We have a spiritual problem. We have a sin problem, and we really desperately need a cure. Now, maybe you're exploring the Christian faith. Maybe there's a part of you right now saying, are you sure we have a spiritual problem? Because I get the people in the story, but they're like ancients.
They're like primitive. We have so much more modern knowledge now. We're so much more advanced and sophisticated. Are you sure? Are you sure we're more sophisticated spiritually today? Are you happy? Are you fully content and satisfied? Is anyone in your life fully happy? And we have unlimited options with Amazon Prime. Are we really happy? In fact, I wonder if that's something that the people in our story may have thought as well. You know, the people who are being bit in our story by the snakes, they are largely comprised of the second generation of God's people in the wilderness.
The first generation, all those who complained and grumbled, they had pretty much for the most part died off. This was now a new rising generation, so maybe there was a part of them that thought, we're not going to be like the first generation. We're going to be more spiritually advanced and sophisticated than they are, but they were just like them. They were like them biologically. They were like them spiritually. They were like them spiritually. And you and I, we are just like those in the wilderness, going all the way back to those who fell in the garden.
We have a sin problem, and we need a cure. And here was God's cure for them in the wilderness. The people then came to Moses and said, we have sinned by speaking against the Lord and against you. Intercede with the Lord so that he will take the snakes away from us. And Moses interceded for the people. And the people said to Moses, make a snake image and mount it on a pole. When anyone who is bitten looks at it, he will recover. So Moses made a bronze snake and mounted it on a pole.
Whenever someone was bitten and he looked at the bronze snake, he recovered. If you work in the medical field or you know someone, this image of a snake wrapped around the pole probably rings a bell. This is a sign or an insignia that's on many medical or hospital-related things, and it's really a symbol of healing. It's, in fact, one of the oldest symbols of healing that we have today. And so this symbol, nothing new for us. It is not strange at all. But imagine how strange it must have been for the people in the story.
They're perishing in the wilderness. They're dying because they've been bitten by the snakes. And then yet, they see Moses, their wise, spiritual leader, make a bronze snake, an image of the very thing that's killing them, raise it on a pole and say, if you want to live, look. Think about how disorienting that must have been for them. Wait, Moses, hold on, let me get this straight. You want me to look at the image of the thing that's killing me right now? Did you hear from God correctly?
So the cure, the cure is to look at the thing that ruined all of humanity. It gets worse, by the way. Do you remember what happened to the serpent in the garden after deceiving Adam and Eve? The snake was cursed. The snake received a curse from God. The snake was cursed by God. And now, you're telling me to look up at the thing that is cursed by God? So the thing that is cursed is to become my cure? It must have been one of the most baffling things that people had ever heard.
It must have sounded like foolishness. Utter foolishness, complete and utter foolishness. And yet, for those that looked, there was power. Power to save, rescue, and heal. And this power in foolishness, it has everything to do with you and the heart of the Christian faith. So approximately 1,500 years after this bizarre scene, we would find one of the first thinkers of the Christian faith by the name of Paul, the Apostle Paul.
He would describe the heartbeat message of the Christian faith in this way in 1 Corinthians 1. For the word of the cross is foolishness to those who are perishing. But it is the power of God to us who are being saved. In other words, Paul the Apostle is saying the center, the core of the Christian faith, it looks like foolishness. But actually, when we look at the cross, there's power. What happened on the cross? Jesus was lifted up.
Jesus was lifted up on the cross. He was raised up on the cross, just like how the bronze serpent was raised up and lifted up on the pole. In fact, Jesus would make this exact same connection in John 3. Jesus said, just as Moses lifted up the snake in the wilderness, so the Son of Man must be lifted up so that everyone who believes in him may have eternal life. Jesus is saying, just as the bronze serpent was lifted up, which gave life, the Son of Man, Jesus, is raised up on the cross who gives eternal life.
But how could Jesus compare himself to the snake? They're nothing alike. How could Jesus, the perfect one, compare himself to the serpent? I mean, the serpent was a liar. Jesus never lied. The serpent came to kill, steal, and destroy. Jesus came to give life and life abundant. So how could he ever compare himself to the serpent? Because of the spiritual principle that was laid in the wilderness, the spiritual template which looked like foolishness but was power, namely, the thing that is cursed can become the cure.
The thing that is cursed by God can become the cure. On the cross, when Jesus was raised up and lifted up, he was cursed. He was cursed by God because he absorbed all the poison of sin and death. All the sin and death that was circulating in your spiritual life, he absorbed into his life and heart. All of our sins, all of our mistakes, the big ones, the small ones, the ones we regret, the ones we probably should regret but don't because of the deceiving power of sin, all of that was poured into Jesus' life.
But in turn, his righteousness, his goodness becomes our cure. Jesus' perfect life becomes the antivenom, the antidote which brings us life and eternal life. The spiritual poison in us was injected into Jesus' spiritual bloodstream and his spiritual life was injected into our spiritual bloodstream, bringing us life. Paul says the exact same thing in 2 Corinthians 5.
God, he made the one Jesus who did not know sin to be sin, to be cursed for us so that in Jesus we might become the righteousness of God. The cursed one becomes our cure. Jesus, he was spiritually cursed that he might become your spiritual cure. This is the gospel. This is the good news of the Christian faith in which there is power in what appears to be foolishness.
And this is how it speaks to you and I today. You know, for those of us who have trusted Jesus, this means that right now in this moment, you can have peace or you can relax. You don't have to look over your shoulders. You don't have to tiptoe around God. You don't have to wonder and with a little bit of anxiousness, how does God feel about me today? Instead, you can simply rest in the fullness of his love. This means you're already secure in God's love.
God's love for you has already been poured out in full. Isn't it true that sometimes when we live the Christian life, we can kind of feel uncomfortable because if we're honest, sometimes we live in a way where our lives don't exactly match up with how we know a follower of Jesus should be living. And sometimes we can even mess up really bad. We can blow it really bad. And there are times when we think, oh gosh, if Christians, if other people knew the kind of week that I had, I feel that way sometimes. Now there's nothing wrong with conviction.
Yeah, when we mess up, when we disobey, we should have a healthy conviction. But if we're not careful, we can actually begin to believe the lie that because I messed up, God must feel differently about me. He must feel differently about me. We can start to think, I don't know if I deserve God's love right now. I don't know if I deserve God's love right now. I have good news for you. You're right. You don't deserve God's love. None of us deserve his love. That's the point.
That's the point of this whole thing. It's grace. It's that he pours out all the wonderful things that we don't deserve. You get God's forgiveness. You get God's righteousness and we don't deserve it. And you already have in full God's love poured out on you already. And by the way, do you know what is the ultimate proof? What's the ultimate evidence and sign that his love has already been poured out on you? Jesus on the cross, the one who is lifted up is the ultimate sign and evidence and demonstration that you're good, that you can relax, that you already fully have his love.
You don't believe me? So you know this passage that we read earlier where Jesus, he makes the connection between him being lifted up and the bronze serpent that's lifted up? Do you know what verse follows next? It surprises a lot of people. It's the most famous passage in all the scriptures. John 3:16. For God loved the world in this way. He gave his one and only son so that everyone who believes in him will not perish but have eternal life.
Notice how Jesus makes the connection between him being raised up on the cross as the ultimate demonstration of his love for you? You already have his love in full. He's already been raised up and lifted up on the cross. You think a little bit of your failure is going to change the way that he feels about you today? He already gave you his son. God already gave you his son. There's nothing left to hold back. There's not a single drop or an ounce of his love that he's withholding from you today.
No, he loves you with his entire being. And so you can rest in his love. And you can know that because Jesus was lifted up on the cross. Now, you might be saying, I believe that intellectually, but I just... I just don't feel it because my faith feels so small and my sin feels so big. Okay, so let's talk it out. Let's rubber ducky this thing. Let's kind of go back to our story for a moment. Don't you think there were all kinds of people who were saved that day?
Let's use our imagination for a moment. There was probably someone in the wilderness who got bit by the smallest snake in the wilderness. Like, they had the least amount of poison circulating through their veins. And when they looked at the bronze serpent, they may have looked with utter confidence, full faith. Did they get healed? They did. But now, there was probably someone else in the camp. Like for this guy, he was the unluckiest guy in the camp that day. He got bit. By the biggest snake in the camp.
He got the most amount of poison, like three gallons of poison minimum. And he may have been totally reluctant. He might have been cynical, pessimistic. This is ridiculous. Why would anyone look at the bronze serpent? But when he reluctantly looked at the snake, was he healed? He was. Was he healed any less than the person with small sin but great faith? Not at all. They were healed exactly the same. Why? Because the power is not on the intensity of your faith.
The power lies in the one who is intensely faithful. The power doesn't lie in the smallness of your sin. No, your sin could be huge. But where your sin abounds, God's grace and love abounds all the more. Like he's a really great Savior. He's a really effective and powerful Savior. You can trust him. You got small faith? You got big sin? Run to him. Run to him. Maybe you're exploring the Christian faith and you're saying, hey, this almost sounds too good to be true. But where's my contribution? This feels really passive right now.
And all the other faith religions, it's about earning, and there's no earning here. What do I do? How can I contribute? Well, let's go back to the story. Let's rubber ducky this thing one more time. You know when God told Moses to command the people to look, was there any other action besides looking? Did Moses tell the people, everyone, look at the bronze serpent, but before you do that, you got to try to suck out as much of the venom from your bitten area as possible. Like you got to reach at least an 85% quota of sucking out the venom before.
No, he didn't say that. Did Moses say, hey, look, but you have to be as close to the bronze serpent as possible. You got to run. If you're far off, run as hard as you can. And then look, Moses did not say that. He simply said, look, look. He did not even qualify the quality of the looking. Moses did not say, look intently. He did not say, look and don't blink for 30 seconds. He simply said, look.
And God simply invites us belief, belief, believe in the beautiful Savior who was raised and lifted up on the cross. It's not our behaving that saves us. It's believing, trusting in Jesus that saves us. In fact, it's not even 99% of your believing with 1% behaving. It's 100% believing.
So if you're tuning in today and you're saying, that's good news because I've got nothing. I've got nothing. I've got nothing. I've got 0% behavior. The good news is that when Jesus was raised up, he brought 100% of perfection for you. And if you trust him right now, you have 100% already of his love in full. You are loved with a strange, bizarre, and unusual love.
So let's sing and let's respond. Let me love you.
I love you, Lord. Oh, your mercy never fails me. And all my days I've been held in your hands. From the moment that I wake up until I lay my head. Oh, I will sing of the goodness of God.
And all my life you have.